Guide to the Richard W. Franke Files on Indonesia and East Timor TAM.590
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Richard W. Franke Files on Indonesia and East Timor
circa 1965-circa 1990
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
TAM.590
8.5 Linear Feet (9 boxes)
Richard W. Franke served as a professor of anthropology at the Montclair State University from 1972 to 2009. He edited the U.S. Tapol Bulletin, the official publication of Tapol USA, from 1975 until 1980. The collection contains files related to political and human rights in Indonesia and East Timor from the 1960s through the 1980s.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials found in collection; provenance is unknown. The accession number associated with this collection is 2011.118.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. Materials are in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Historical/Biographical Note
Richard W. Franke served as a professor of anthropology at the Montclair State University from 1972 to 2009. He edited the U.S. Tapol Bulletin, the official publication of Tapol USA, from 1975 until 1980. The UK-based Tapol was initially formed in 1973 as an advocacy organization to support political prisoners in Indonesia. Their mission later expanded to encompass general human rights concerns in Indonesia and East Timor. The now defunct U.S. branch of Tapol was located in Montclair, New Jersey. Franke also wrote extensively on East Timor and Indonesia for many publications, including the Guardian and the Bulletin of Concerned Asian Scholars.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
East Timor and Indonesia Action Network (ETAN) Records (TAM 393)
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains files related to political and human rights in Indonesia and East Timor from the 1960s through the 1980s. The advocacy and other activities of Tapol and its U.S. branch makes up a significant portion of the collection. It also includes information on the work of Amnesty International and other human rights organizations.
Separated Materials
Approximately one hundred issues of the Tapol Bulletin (UK), Tapol Bulletin (US), Southeast Asian Chronicle, Indonesia: feiten en meningen, and the East Timor Estafeta were separated for cataloging, as were a couple dozen books.
Indonesia |x History |y 1966-1998; Timor-Leste |x History.; Human rights |z Indonesia.; Human rights |z Timor-Leste.; Franke, Richard W.; Tapol (Organization); Tapol--USA (Organization); Amnesty International
- Inventory
  - Publications on Indonesian Economics, Correspondence, Statements to United Nations General Assembly, International Conference on East Timor and Indonesia, Clippings (including the Congressional Record), and UN Press Releases, circa 1968 - circa 1986 (Box 1)
  - East Timor and the United Nations and Timor Information Service Publications; and Correspondence, Clippings, and Academic Conference Papers on East Timor and Indonesia, circa 1975 - 1982 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence (mostly Amnesty International), Academic Conference Papers, Petitions/Advocacy for East Timor, and Publications on Indonesia, 1968 - 1982 (Box 3)
  - Congressional Hearings, Clippings, Publications on Human Rights in East Timor, Addresses to United Nations on East Timor, Academic Papers, and Buttons, circa 1976 - 1982 (Box 4)
  - Letters to and Testimony Before Congress on East Timor, Academic Papers, Clippings, Reports on Military Situation in East Timor, and Congressional Hearings, circa 1976 - 1984 (Box 5)
  - Permanent People's Tribunal in Lisbon (1981), Manuscript "Impasse in Java's Agriculture: A Case for Chinese Style Collectivization" by R.R. Smith, Informational Publications on Indonesia, Manuscript About 1965 Coup, East Timor Advocacy, and Academic Papers, circa 1974 - 1990 (Box 6)
  - East Timor Human Rights Advocacy Publications, Clippings, Correspondence (mostly related to Tapol US and UK), and Statements before the United Nations on East Timor and Indonesia, circa 1974 - 1985 (Box 7)
  - Clippings, Photographs, Academic Papers, Permanent People's Tribunal in Lisbon, Prisons in Indonesia, East Timor Famine, Papers by Noam Chomsky, and Information on West Irian, 1965 - 1982 (Box 8)
  - Film "Isle of Fear, Isle of Hope," Two Posters, and Bumper Stickers, undated (Box 9)